"Preventing and Treating Essential
Hand Tremor with Diet"
As documented in the book
The Case of the Frozen Addicts,
a bad batch of so-called
synthetic heroin
caused, within days,
what appeared to be
advanced-stage
Parkinson’s disease.
Thanks to a chemical contaminant
known as MPTP,
young men and women
were left trapped
inside their bodies,
with near complete immobility,
in some cases able
to move only their eyes.
The seminal paper
describing the phenomenon
ended with the silver lining
that maybe this will help us
find the culprit in Parkinson’s.
Attention turned
to a class of chemicals
called beta-carboline alkaloids
due to their structural
similarity to MPTP.
And, indeed, higher levels
of these toxins
were found in the brain fluid
of Parkinson’s patients.
In How Not to Die,
I address Parkinson’s,
since it’s one
of our leading killers,
but the most common
movement disorder
is what’s called
"essential tremor,"
affecting up to 1 in 25
adults older than 40,
and up to 1 in 5
people in their 90s.
In addition to the potentially
debilitating hand tremor,
there can be other
neurological manifestations,
including cognitive impairment,
depression,
and sleeping problems.
In medical lingo, "essential"
can mean "of unknown cause,"
like essential hypertension,
the rise in blood pressure
as we age.
Just as there have been
calls for decades
to rename that phenomenon
once it became clear
that lifestyle behaviors
played a critical role,
there are those suggesting
we rename essential tremor
as we come to understand
it better as well.
Identical twin studies
suggest it may only be
60 percent genetic.
Though there have been
studies linking
the development
of essential tremor
to lead exposure,
most attention has focused
on beta-carboline alkaloids.
Beta-carboline alkaloids
induce tremor
in a wide variety of animals,
from mice to monkeys,
that’s similar
to essential tremor in humans
both clinically
and in the type
of brain damage they cause.
As such, beta-carboline
alkaloid administration
produces the main animal
model for essential tremor
upon which to try out new drugs.
Harmane is the most potent
of these tremor-producing
beta-carboline alkaloids.
Expose people
to high dose harmane,
and they develop tremors too;
take it away,
and the tremors disappear.
What if we’re exposed
to small doses over time?
All six studies found that
those with essential tremor
have significantly higher
levels of this toxin
in their bloodstream
compared to those
without tremor-
five out of six
significantly so.
Furthermore, the higher
the harmane levels,
the worse the tremor.
The highest levels are found
in those who have both
essential tremor and cancer,
suggesting harmane
may be playing a role
in both diseases.
Elevated harmane levels
have also been found
directly in the brains
of essential tremor
patients on autopsy.
Due to its high fat solubility,
harmane accumulates
in brain tissue.
Using a fancy brain scan called
"protein magnetic resonance
spectroscopic imaging,"
higher harmane levels
were found to be
a significant predictor
of signs of nerve degeneration
in the cerebellum,
the part of the brain
that controls movement.
How do we get exposed
to these chemicals?
Small amounts of harmane
are produced endogenously
but the main source is meat.
Beta carboline alkaloids
are a type
of heterocyclic amine,
the class of carcinogens
that are formed
in a high-temperature
chemical reaction
between some of the components
of muscle tissue.
Under the same
cooking conditions
chicken may produce
the most harmane
(more than twice as much
as beef steak, for example),
but the highest
single per-serving levels
have been found in fried pork,
flame-broiled steak,
flame-broiled chicken,
and grilled salmon.
Researchers gave people
a slice of fried turkey
and saw a bump
in harmane blood levels
within five minutes.
Five minutes?
It’s not even digested by then.
The researchers suspect
the rapid uptake
is indicative
of significant absorption
directly through the mouth
and straight
into the bloodstream,
bypassing the stomach
and, most importantly,
bypassing the detoxifying
enzymes of the liver
before it makes it up
into our brain.
So, if this "potent,
tremor-producing neurotoxin"
is concentrated
in "cooked muscle foods,"
is meat consumption
associated with a higher risk
of essential tremor?
A study
out of Columbia University
found that men
who ate the most meat
(about 1.5 servings a day)
had a whopping 21 times
the odds of essential tremor
compared to men who ate
closer to a half serving a day.
To put that in context,
if we go back
to the original studies
on smoking and lung cancer,
we see that smoking
was only linked
to about 14 times the odds.
Now, arguing against meat’s role
in essential tremor
through harmane exposure
is the fact that
a similar relationship
was not found in women,
and there appeared to be
no difference in tremor rates
between those
who preferred their meat
rare versus well-cooked.
A reverse causation
explanation was also proposed:
instead of greater
meat consumption
leading to essential tremor,
perhaps the essential tremor
led to greater meat consumption,
as a solid stable food
that may be more easily
handled with a tremulous hand.
Or perhaps the elevated
harmane levels in tremor victims
is due to a reduced
capacity to detoxify it
or a combination
of greater intake
and lesser excretion.
For those reluctant
to reduce their
meat consumption,
different marinades
have been tested
to reduce harmane production.
Hibiscus extracts
seemed to make things worse
and so did red wine,
increasing formation
up to 10-fold.
However, a Caribbean marinade
and a variety
of berry extracts worked.
For example,
marinating camel meat
in strawberry juice
for 24 hours before frying
can reduce
the formation of harmane
by as much as 40 percent.
Are there any
dietary treatments
once you already
have the disease?
Vanillin--the primary
fragrance compound
in vanilla extract--
was found to be beneficial
against beta-carboline-induced
tremors in rats,
but there have yet to be
any clinical studies.